Whenever you insure any vehicle like a car,
bike, scooter, truck or
any commercial vehicle, then whenever
you insure any vehicle,
you must have heard about first party,
second party, third party. What does it mean? Let me
explain all these things because
many people are confused, they do not understand what first party is, second party, they understand
something else which is not actually there,
they assume it on their own, which if
they understand like this, it will be harmful for them. So
I am going to clear everything for you in this video, so
watch this video carefully, what is first party, what is
second party insurance, and what is
third party insurance, what do all
three insurances mean, I will
explain everything in this video, so let's
start. So hi everyone, my name is
Vijay and you are watching Vijay Solution, so first of all let me
tell you what is first party
insurance. Look, first
party insurance is also
called comprehensive, okay, so you can say first party.
Or make it comprehensive, it is your
first party, in this when you do first
party, the meaning of first party is that
many people think that the owner of the car,
who is the first owner of the car, is the first party, it is
not so, whether you are the
first owner, second owner or
tenth owner of a car, you are doing first party
insurance, not party, okay, the party is
not being insured, your car is insured,
your car is first party, okay, so
understand that the party of your vehicle is the
first party, not its owner,
whoever is the first party owner, even if
it is sold or transferred 10 times, it does
not matter, the
first party is your car, okay, so it is the
insurance of that car, not of the
car owner, so you should not
think that if we have bought a second hand car, then
we will do second party, it does not happen like this, so
you should not understand these things, that is what
I was saying that in first party, the
first party is your car,
which you insure,
when you do insurance in this,
your car is covered in it,  In case of any
kind of accident, damage
or in any other way if your vehicle gets destroyed then
you
get a claim from the insurance company. Now in this,
many people
think that Zero Depth is a separate
insurance in the first party itself. It gets added to the comprehensive insurance.
Now what happens in Zero Depth is that if you do
comprehensive normally, like you did
not add Zero Depth, you did only
Comprehensive, that means you did First Party
and did not add Zero Depth, then you do
not have bumper to bumper insurance.
You can approximately take an average that
you will get a claim between 70 to 80 percent. If there is
any damage to your vehicle then you have to pay the
rest of the money yourself. If you
do normal, that means you do not take Zero Depth,
then Zero Depth is not like that
for 15 years, it is covered only for 5 years,
and in 5 years
if you do not take claim then it remains for one or two years.  And if
any other company gives it to you, that is a different matter,
but normally you should understand that zero depth is
available only for 5 years, so you understand
that if you take simple comprehensive
or first party as you call it, then you
get insurance claim on 70% of your vehicle and if you
take zero depth, then in zero depth you get
bumper to bumper insurance of your vehicle
and whatever
your expenses are in it, almost 95% means 100%,
let's say the insurance company pays 100%,
you have to pay a lot of money
and the file charges are the same, so
in zero depth,
you will be absolutely free, if any
kind of accident happens or something happens, if there is
any expense in your vehicle, then the
insurance company will pay all the money, if you
take zero depth, then ok, so this is the
first party, now you will ask who is the second party, then whichever
insurance company you took insurance from,
whichever company you
took insurance from, that automatically becomes the second party.
And the insurance company is always a second party,
so do not think that the car owner has
bought it from another owner, that means the car has been transferred from one owner
to another, so he is the
second party, no, the insurance company is
always the second party in any insurance,
okay, so this second party will be the
insurance company and there is no one else,
after that comes the third party
insurance, okay, so there is always the first
party, either there is third party insurance, there is
no second party insurance,
but people get confused, that is why I said
second party because there is only the
insurance company in any case,
okay, so let's come to the third party,
so in third party it means
only the third person, it means
that suppose your car caused any
loss to someone, okay, suppose you
broke someone's wall, there was an accident, then
his wall got broken, now the wall which got broken,
or suppose you
rammed it into someone's shop, then whatever damage was caused to his goods, then
he becomes the third party, okay, the person whose
goods got damaged or whose wall got broken, that person becomes the
third party, so if you have
taken only third party insurance, then there
is some insurance for your car  No,
because you have taken only third party
insurance, so the insurance company
which is the second party, because I have
told you that there is second party insurance, so
what will the insurance company do, that is, the second
party will pay the money to the third party,
because you have taken insurance from the third party as well, so if
your car causes
any damage to someone, whether you
ram into someone's shop and cause damage to him,
or you break someone's wall, you break someone's
house or cause any damage to anyone, then the
second party, that is, the
insurance company, will pay him the money, you do
n't have to pay, so this is the difference between the
first party, second party and third
party, there is nothing else, so this is a
small thing, first party means your
car is covered, that is, first party means
your car, second party means the
insurance company, and third party means
that if someone else is harmed by your car, then that is the
third party, the
third party is not fixed, you can hit anyone, you can
cause immeasurable damage to anyone, so this is not fixed,
but both the first party and the party
are fixed, that is, the first party can be your
car, the second party can be the insurance company, and
anyone can be in the third party, I hope everything is fine.  You must have
understood it, if there
is still some confusion or you did not understand something then
ask by commenting below, I will
try to cover it in the next video, for
now this is all for this video,
thank you very much.